<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A verie perfect discourse, and order hovv to know the age of a horse and the diseases that breede in him, with the remedies to cure the same: as also, the description of euery veyne, and how and when to let him blood, according to the diuersitie of the disease: as hath been proued by the author L.W.C.</title>
            <author>L. W. C.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1601</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17464</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4286</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113441</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848675</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848675</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13786</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17464)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13786)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 678:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A verie perfect discourse, and order hovv to know the age of a horse and the diseases that breede in him, with the remedies to cure the same: as also, the description of euery veyne, and how and when to let him blood, according to the diuersitie of the disease: as hath been proued by the author L.W.C.</title>
                  <author>L. W. C.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By VV. VV[hite] for Thomas Pauier,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1601.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf bears a woodcut of a horse.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Approued remedies for diseased horses.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; E4, final leaf, torn, with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Horses --  Age --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Horses --  Diseases --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13786:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> VERIE Perfect Diſcourſe, and order hovv to know the Age of a HORSE, and the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes that breede in him with the Remedies to cure the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>me as alſo.</p>
            <p>The deſcription of euery Vayne, and how and when to let him Blood, according to the diuerſitie of the Diſeaſe: as hath been proued by the Author L. W. C.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at London by VV.VV. for <hi>Thomas Fauier.</hi> 160<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:13786:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram of horse anatomy</figDesc>
                  <p>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>he 2 Templev</item>
                        <item>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>he 2 ey v</item>
                        <item>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>he 2 forehead</item>
                        <item>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>he 2 pallet v</item>
                        <item>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>he 2 necke ve</item>
                        <item>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>he 2 plate ve</item>
                        <item>The 2 fore ſhanck v</item>
                        <item>The z ſide veyn</item>
                        <item>The Shanck</item>
                        <item>The houf</item>
                        <item>The taie veyn.</item>
                        <item>The hanch ve</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:13786:2"/>
            <head>In this Diſcourſe is fyrſt ſhewed how, and when, a Horſe ſhould be let blood, and to what end, and by what ſigne a man may know whether it be requiſite or no Secondly. in how many Vaynes he may be let Blood. Thirdly, how to know his Age. Fourthly, where all kind of diſeaſes do grow, and how to cure them.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How and when a Horſe ſhould be let blood, and to what end, and by what ſigne a man may know whether it be requiſite or no.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, to preſerue health, it is good to let him Blood foure times a yeere. Firſt in the Spring about the beginning of May, becauſe the Blood beginneth to increaſe.</p>
               <p>Secondly, in September, becauſe the blood being then inflamed inequally, may euaporate or breake out.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, about the middeſt of December, to let out the groſſe and knottie Blood.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, about the middeſt of March.</p>
               <p>But I would not with you to let a Horſe blood but once a yeere, and that in the beginning of May, within a fortnight after his putting to graſſe: for then you ſhall let out the groſſe and old blood, and the new will come in his place. Except it be vpon great need, I would wiſh you not to let
<pb facs="tcp:13786:3"/>
him blood at all: for oft letting blood, cauſeth debſlitie in the Horſe, it hindreth the ſight, and maketh the blood to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort inwardly, which cloyeth the Hart and Intralles, and leaueth the outwarde partes deſtitute.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In how many Vaynes an Horſe may be let blood.</head>
               <p>IN the firſt 2. Vaynes are the Temple Vaynes, which be the principall Vaines in the Head.</p>
               <p>In the 2. Eye Vaynes, which are eaſie to find in the face of the Horſe ſomewhat beneath his eyes.</p>
               <p>In the 2. Pallet Vaines in the mouth.</p>
               <p>In the 2. Necke Vaynes.</p>
               <p>In the 2. Plate Vaynes, which are in the Breſt.</p>
               <p>In the 2. Forehead Vaynes.</p>
               <p>In the 2. fore Shanke Vaynes before.</p>
               <p>In the 2. fore Vaynes before.</p>
               <p>In the 2. ſide Vaines, which may be called y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Scanke vaines.</p>
               <p>In the Tayle Vayne.</p>
               <p>In the Hanch Vayne.</p>
               <p>In the Hoofe Vaynes.</p>
               <p>In the 2. fore Shanke Vaynes behind.</p>
               <p>So by this account, an Horſe may be let Blood in 31. Vaynes: all which Vaynes are eaſie enough to know, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe euery one lyeth in a little gutter, which you ſhall finde by feeling with your finger.</p>
               <p>If your Horſe be payned with any griefe in his head, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uineſſe Franſey, Fawling euyll, or ſuch like, then it is good to let him blood in the Temple Vaines with a Fleme.</p>
               <p>If his Eyes be wateriſh or Blood-ſhotten, or greened with Pinne or Webbe or Haw, then it is good to ſet him Blood in the Eye Vayne with a Fleme.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13786:3"/>If he haue any wearineſſe or heauineſſe of Body, or be diſeaſed in the Throat with the Stranglings or Squianſy, or ſwellinges of the Artires either within or without, then it is good to let blood in the Pallet Vaynes in the Mouth with a Coruet.</p>
               <p>If he be vexed with an Ague, or with any other diſeaſe vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall hurting his body, then let him blood in the Necke Vaines.</p>
               <p>If his griefe be in the Lunges, Lyuer, or any other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward part, then let him blood in the Breſt Vaines: which we call (before) the Plate Vaynes.</p>
               <p>If he be greeued in the Soulders, then let him blood in the Fore-feete Vaines aboue the knee with a Launce, and that very warely: for that place is full of Sinniewes.</p>
               <p>If he be greeued in the Ioyntes, then let him blood in the Shackle Vaynes, and that very warely: for that place is ful of Sinniewes alſo.</p>
               <p>If he be foyled in the Fore-feete with Foundring or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, then let him blood in the two Vaynes (make way firſt with your Drawer to come to your vaines) in the Fore-feete.</p>
               <p>If he be diſeaſed in the Kidnyes or Reynes, Backe or Belly, then let him blood in the Flancke Vaynes.</p>
               <p>If he haue any griefe in his Hippes, then let him blood in the Tayle Vaine or Hough Vayne.</p>
               <p>If his hinder Legges be greeued, or Ioyntes, or Feete, then let him blood on the Shackle Vaines, and on the 2. Vaines behinde on the hinder feete.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:13786:4"/>
               <head>To know the age of a Horſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A</hi> Horſe hath xl. Teeth, the xxx. Moneth after his foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling he loſeth two aboue and two beneath: in the iiii. yeere he loſeth two aboue and two beneath: when he is fiue he caſteth all the reſt both aboue and beneath. Thoſe that come firſt aboue are hollow: when he is ſixe, his hollow Teeth are filled vp, and in the. vii all the reſt are filled vp: then you can no longer iudge of his age by his Teeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To know where theſe Diſeaſes do grow about a Horſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>BAgges,</hi> is in the weakes of the Mouth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Barbe,</hi> be two Teates growing vnder the Tongue.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bottes,</hi> do grow and breed in the Maw and Guttes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bliſters</hi> on his body, commeth through heate and cold.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Camer,</hi> is in his Mouth venomed, and will make his tongue to haue cliftes and ſcabbes in his vpper Lippes vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neath, and are full of blacke Wheales or Pimples, ſo that he can hardly eate his meate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Coult Euill,</hi> is by ranckneſſe of Water and Blood, it will cauſe his Belly and Yeard to ſwell.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cloying,</hi> is in the Hoofe of the Feete.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cordes,</hi> is a ſlacke Sinniew in the Legges before.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Curbes,</hi> is a ſwelling Sinniew behind the Hooſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Crotches,</hi> is a ruffe ſcurffineſſe aboue the Fetter-lockes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Interfeering,</hi> is ſtriking on the Ioynt about the Paſtorne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Farcion</hi> or <hi>Farcie,</hi> is a Scabbe or Knobbes breaking in diuers places of his body, &amp; commeth chiefly in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Vaines.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Feuer,</hi> is a ſickneſſe taken with cold, and will cauſe him to ſhake.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thiſtula,</hi> is an old rotten Sore in his Body.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13786:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Foundering,</hi> is taken in the Body, and Feete alſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fraying,</hi> is taken in the Body, and Feete, and Legges, which is a ſtifneſſe comming onely with cold.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Frounce</hi> or <hi>Pimples</hi> in the Pallet of his Mouth, Gawling, or other hurt, and come eſpecially by eating of frozen graſſe or duſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gigges</hi> or <hi>Flappes,</hi> are Pimples or Teates on the inſide of the Mouth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Glaunders,</hi> are Curnels vnder his Iawes, and when they are ripe, they will runne at his Noſe, and ſo breake out.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gorge,</hi> is a ſwelling of Blood in the Legges.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Graueling,</hi> is taken in the Feete.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Webbe</hi> in the Eye or the <hi>Haw,</hi> which is a Griſſell growing on the Felme, which ſcowreth the Eye.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hyde-bound,</hi> is when the Skinne cleaueth to the Fleſh and the Ribbes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hoofe-bound,</hi> is in the pinching of the Hoofe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Itch in the Tayle,</hi> is by exceſſe of Blood.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lampas,</hi> is the Fleſh in the Mouth nie the vpper Teeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mange,</hi> is taken by ſome Scabbe or byting.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mallander,</hi> is a Scabbe in the bone of the Knees.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Molt-long,</hi> is the pinching of a ſtraight Hoofe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mourning of the Chine,</hi> is a waſting from the Backe, or broken Winded.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nauell galled,</hi> is a ſore on his Backe againſt the Nauell, or an Impoſtume ſore.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paynes,</hi> is a ſoreneſſe about the Hoofe, or Foote-lockes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Powle-euill,</hi> is on the nape of the Necke, and breedeth by ſtripes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pinne</hi> or <hi>Webbe,</hi> which couereth the beard of the Eye.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rume,</hi> is taken by cold, and ſo his Teeth will waxe looſe and ſeeme long, and then he cannot eate his meate, but it will lie in lumpes, and about his Iawes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ring-bone,</hi> is a hard Griſtle about the Hoofe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quinaſie,</hi> is a ſoreneſſe in the Throate.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13786:5"/>
                  <hi>Sclander,</hi> is a Scab on the Hammes on the hinder Legges</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Shackle gawled,</hi> is on the Paſtorne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Spauen,</hi> is on the Ioynt in the Hoofes behinde.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Splent,</hi> is a ſplend Sinniew aboue the Fetter lockes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Staggers,</hi> is a dooſineſſe in the Head, breeding of cold, and of the Pellowes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Stranglings,</hi> is a ſwelling of the Throate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e</hi> in a Horſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Surbating,</hi> is vnder the Sooles of the Feete on the further ſide.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Viues,</hi> is a certane Curnell vnder the Eares, or a Canker in the Mouth or Throate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Windgalles,</hi> are Bladders aboue the Fetter-lockes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yellow,</hi> is a kinde of Iaundies, and will cauſe the Eyes to looke yellow, and other partes of the body alſo.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:13786:5"/>
            <head>APPROVED REME<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DIES FOR THE CVRING of any kind of diſeaſe, hurt, maine, or maladie, in Horſes.</head>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Gawling of a Horſe.</head>
               <p>TAke Butter, Vineger, and Bay-ſalt, and melt them together, and lay on the Horſe backe warme: then ſtraw vpon it Sutte, or the powder of a Clay wall.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>An other for the ſame.</head>
               <p>TAke <hi>ob.</hi> of Turmerace, bruſe it: a handfull of Bay ſalt, and a handfull of Sutte, with two handfulls of Oatemeale, mingle it with Vrine, and make it into a cake as well as you can, and then vpon a hot harth bake it till it be burnt blacke, then beat it into powder: and when you haue waſhed your Horſe backe with Lie very hotte, or Chamberlie, then ſtraw on the Powder: and when the Powder is almoſt gone, then dreſſe it as aforeſayd.</p>
               <p>If it be feſtered, take Yeeſt, Hony, the white of an Egge, and Sutte, mingle them togither, and make a Playſter thereof, and lay it to eate the dead fleſh, then ſtraw on Verdegreace, and renew it once a day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:13786:6"/>
               <head>An other for the ſame.</head>
               <p>TAke a Pottle of Vergis, two penny worth of greene Coparis, and boyle it to a pint and a halfe: waſh and ſearch the hole therewith, then fill the hole with redde Lead, and ſo let it remaine three dayes vntouched: then waſh it with the ſame, and fill it againe with the redde Lead: and ſo euery other day waſh it with that water, not made ſo ſtrong of the Coparis, and lay thereon red Lead. This will heale it though it be galled to the body.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>An other for the ſame.</head>
               <p>TAke of the ſtrongeſt Beere a pint, put into it a quarter of a pound of Allum, and halfe a handfull of Sage: ſeeth it to the one halfe, then take out the Sage leaues: This will heale any Canker or Sore in a Horſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>To heale any Cut in a Horſe.</head>
               <p>TAke a quarter of a pound of freſh Butter, of Tarre, and blacke Sope, halfe ſo much of each, and a litle Turpentine: boyle them altogether (but the Sope) and as ſoone as you take it from the fire, put in the Sope, and then vſe it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a Horſe wrong in the Wales.</head>
               <p>TAke Butter and Salt, and boyle them together till they are blacke: then powre it in on hot, then take vp a flake of Doung that is hot, and lay it on the ſore backe, and ſo dreſſe him till he be w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ole.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:13786:6"/>
               <head>For Fretting on the Bellie, which commeth with gawling of the fore Gyrt.</head>
               <p>THis commeth with the fore Gyrt, and it ſtoppeth the Blood which is in the principall Veynes, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Plate Veynes, which do runne length wayes: Take Oyle of Bayes and Oyle of Balme, two ounces of Pitch, two ounces of Tarre, one ounce of Roſen, mingle them altogether and annoynt the foure Bowels: then take Floxe and lay vpon it, and feare it with a hot Yron: but take heed it be not too hot, for feare of burning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For Thiſtulaes.</head>
               <p>VVHen you firſt perceiue it to ſwell, then ſcalde it with Hony and Sheepes Shuet: but ſcald it very much: This will keepe it from bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
               <p>Then take and ſlit it in the neather end of the Sore, and put as much <hi>Mercurie Sublimatum</hi> as a Peaſe, abate it with Sallet Oyle, laying it on with a Fether<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> after that take Verdegreace. iiii. d. worth, Vitreall <hi>ob.</hi> Lead .iii. d. worth, beat theſe together, and euery day waſh the wound with Copris water made with Copris and Elder leaues in Sommer, and with the inner greene Barke in Winter: after the waſhing take the powder, and put it on the Sore, and after it drop on a litle Oyle.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:13786:7"/>
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>TAke the vttermoſt greene ſhelles of Wal-Nuttes, and put them in a Tubbe ſtrowing three or foure handfull of Bay ſalt vpon them, ſome in the bottome, ſome in the middle, and ſome on the toppe, and ſo keepe them all the yeere: and when you will vſe them, take a pint of them and a litle Bay ſalt, and halfe a quarter of a pound of blacke Sope, with halfe a ſponefull of May Butter (and for want thereof, other Butter) and incorporate them togither, and then ſpread it on the ſore: But two howers before you lay it on, annoynt the ſore with a litle <hi>Venis</hi> Turpentine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>A Medecine to kill the Thiſtula cleane.</head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Vnguentum Egipſiacu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> which is made of Hony a pint, Vineger <hi>di.</hi> a pint, Allum a quarter of a pound, and Vergrece i. oz. <hi>di</hi> and ſeeth them altogither till they be thicke and a tawwe colour: this is called <hi>Egi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſiacum:</hi> and to make it the ſtrongeſt way, is to put in <hi>Sublimat.</hi> i. oz. made in powder, and Arſenicke two ſcruples, and boyle it together.</p>
               <p>This ſtrongeſt is for Thiſtulaes, Cankers, and foule Soares: and the firſt may be vſed in the mouth, but not that which is made of <hi>Sublimatum,</hi> and Arſenice, for they are poyſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>A Tent to put into the hollow place of the Thiſtula.</head>
               <p>TAke of <hi>Sublimatum</hi> wel powdered i. oz. the middeſt of well leauoned Bread ſlacke baked, iiii. oz. of <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>n.</hi> x. drammes, mingle them together with a litle Roſe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:13786:7"/>
and make Tentes thereof, and dry them vpon a Tile, and then take it to your vſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>To make Lie for the ſame, or Water, to kill it at the bottome.</head>
               <p>TAke Lie, Hony, Roach Allome, and Mercury, and ſeeth them together, and apply it to the Thiſtula at the bottome thereof.</p>
               <p>Alſo, to dry a Thiſtula, take red Wine, Goates doung, and Beane flower, and ſeeth them together, and lay it on: and this will dry it vp.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>To ſinke a Thiſtula.</head>
               <p>TAke firſt and ſeere it, as with this marke ⊗, and then take Roſen, Sheepes tallow, and Brimſtone, and boyle them together, and lay it on very hot with a cloath: this will ſinke it downe againe. This is good alſo for a Windgall: take and pricke it out (but beware of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes) and then lay it on, but not too hot, but very reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably, and this will keepe it cleane.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a Thiſtula in the head.</head>
               <p>TAke the iuce of Houſe-leeke, and dippe a locke of Wooll in it, and put the locke of Wool in his eares and bind it faſt: vſe this once a day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>An other for the ſame.</head>
               <p>IF there be any Inflamation in the Eares, or that it groweth to an Impoſtumation in that place, you ſhall boyle the rootes of Mallowes in water till they waxe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:13786:8"/>
tender, then bruſe them, and ſtraine out the water cleaner and being warme, giue it the Horſe to drinke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>To know the Bottes.</head>
               <p>WHen you thinke your Horſe hath the Bottes, looke in his mouth and ſmell to his breath, for it will ſtinke, and his mouth will be full of ſlyme.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>To cure the Bottes.</head>
               <p>TAke as much blacke Sope as a Wall-nut, as much Brimſtone beaten, and a litle Garlicke, and put it in good Ale, and giue it the Horſe blood warme: but for a Mare with foole, then take Brimſtone, Sutte, and Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke, without Sope.</p>
               <p>Take a handfull of new Hennes doung, and a quart of good ſtale drinke, and all to bray it with your handes: then take a good handfull of Bay ſalt, and put two Egges to it, and bray them altogether, and giue it your Horſe to drinke in a Horne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>An other for the ſame.</head>
               <p>TAke a pint of Milke, <hi>ob.</hi> of Saffron, <hi>ob.</hi> of Allum, beate them together, and giue it him to drinke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>To kill the Woormes in the Maw.</head>
               <p>TAke the Crops of young Broome, and of Sauen, and Grounſell, of each a quantitie: then choppe them ſmall, and giue it him with his Prouender euening and morning: and let him not drinke for a good ſpace after.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:13786:8"/>If he haue the long Woormes, take Milke, Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, and Hony, and giue him to drinke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For Woormes in the Coddes.</head>
               <p>TAke the Guttes of a young Pullet, and caſt it into his mouth faſting, and make him to ſwallow them downe: do this three morninges together, but let him not drinke or eate in fiue howers after.</p>
               <p>Some vſe to giue him freſh Broome in his prouende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ſalt Water, to drinke.</p>
               <p>Others do giue him of greene Willow, or greene Reede, to eate: and in diſgeſtion of the meate, he ſhall caſt out the Woormes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>An other for the ſame.</head>
               <p>TAke the Garbidge of a young Henne or Pidgion while it is warme, rowle it firſt in a little blacke Sope, and after in Bay-ſalt, and force it downe his throate, and it will helpe him. <hi>Probatum.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>To know when a Horſe hath Woormes.</head>
               <p>TAke vp his vpper Lippe, and you ſhall ſee many ſmall blew Veynes, greater and bigger then the Woorme veynes by a great deale.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a Horſe that hath the Trunchons.</head>
               <p>LEt him drinke Hennes doung. Myntes, Sage, and Rue: and let him blood in the Noſtrilles, or els giue him Sauen or Sothernewood to drinke, and it will cure him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:13786:9"/>
               <head>An other for the ſame.</head>
               <p>TAke <hi>ob.</hi> of <hi>Arment. ob.</hi> of Hony, <hi>ob.</hi> of Venycreke, <hi>ob.</hi> of good ſtale Ale, mingle them together, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e vp the Horſe head on high, and giue it him to drinke with a Horne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For Bliſters.</head>
               <p>TAke the iuce of ground Iuie, with ſo much Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, a quantitie of Tarre, and ſo much Allum: put it all together, and lay it to the Bliſter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Barbes.</head>
               <p>IF they grow long, they will hinder his feeding: they do vſe to clip them with a paire of Sheares, and then waſh his mouth with Water and Salt, and that will cure him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Staggers.</head>
               <p>YOu ſhall perceiue them by beating his head, and he wilbe as though he were blinde.</p>
               <p>Take Garlicke, Rue, and Bay-ſalt and beat them groſly, and put Vineger into it, and put it into the Horſe eares, and then wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Wooll in this medecine and ſtop his cares therewith and bind them cloſe, and let it be ſo xxiiii. howers, and then pull out his Tongue and waſh it with Vineger to make him haue a good ſtomacke.</p>
               <p>Firſt, take a wiſpe of wet Hay and burne it vnder his noſe, that the ſmoake may goe into his head, then take halfe a handfull of Salandine, and as much Hearbe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:13786:9"/>
Graſſe, three or foure cloue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Garlike, and a litle Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalt, and ſtampe them together, and put thereto foure or fiue ſpoonefull of Vineger or Verges: then cramme it into the Horſe cares, &amp; tie the eares cloſe that no ayre may come in: let it continue in his eares a day and a night, and then let him blood.</p>
               <p>Or els take Rue and Salandine of each a like, and white Salt, and ſtampe them together, and put it into his eares, and then binde them vp for two howers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>An other for the ſame.</head>
               <p>TAke Oyle of bitter Almondes, i. Oz. <hi>di.</hi> of Oxe gall, two Drammes of blacke <hi>Ellabar</hi> ſtamped, <hi>ob.</hi> of Grames, of <hi>Caſterum,</hi> of Vineger, and of Varuice. v. drammes: ſeeth them altogether till the Vineger be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed: then ſtraine them, and put it into his cates.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the paine in the Head, or ſtifeling.</head>
               <p>KEepe his Head warme, and let him drinke warme Water mindgled with Wheate meale or Fennell-ſeedes, and blow it into his noſe with a quill, and ſome powder of <hi>Ellab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r</hi> or Neeſing powder, mixed together with ſome Pepper: then take a pint of Malme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey, the whites and yolkes of. v. new layde Egges, one head of Garlicke bruied, ſmall Pepper, Sinamon and Nutmegs beaten ſine, and a quantitie of ſweete Butters mingle them all together, and giue to him to drinke three dayes after: but let him not drinke in foure howers after.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:13786:10"/>
               <head>For the Wanders.</head>
               <p>TAke halfe a buſhell of Barley and ſet it on the fire in a yanne, and put thereto running water, and euer as the water waſteth put in more, ſo that the Barley be couered with water, and let it ſeeth till the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley be broken: then take a little Poake or Sacke and put the Barley therein, and lay the ſame on the Horſe ridge on length from the Mane to the Cropper al hot, and let it lie till it be cold, and there let it lie a nyght and a day, and put the Horſe into a greene Yarde ſome. xx iii. howers, and there he will wallow: and then take him in, and he will be whole.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Yellowes.</head>
               <p>YOu ſhall know them by the white of his eye, which wilbe yellow: or elſe by his tongue, which will haue yellow vaines: or elſe put vp his vpper lyppe, and you ſhall ſee the vaines yellow.</p>
               <p>Take two races of Turmeracke, and <hi>ob.</hi> of Saffron, and put it in a pint of ſtrong Beere or Ale, and warme it blood warme, and giue it him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>An other for the ſame.</head>
               <p>TAke Turmeracke a cloue <hi>et di. et di.</hi> a doſen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hinnes of Saffron, one or two Cloues, and ſixe ſponefulles of Vineger or Verges: and put in each care three ſponefull, and ſtoppe his eares with blacke Wooll: and then tie them faſt, vii. or .viii. dayes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>An other for the ſame.</head>
               <p>TAke long Pepper, Graynes, Turmeracke, and Lyco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris beaten into powder: put them into ſtrong Beere, and giue it him to drinke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:13786:10"/>
               <head>For the paynes or Crotches which commeth by heate and the ſodaine cold vpon it.</head>
               <p>THe paynes appeare about the Hoofe, you ſhall know them by the haire ſtanding right vp: you muſt take vp the Shackle vaynes on both ſides, then take the ſoft row of a red Hearing, and Muſtard, and blacke Sope, and boyle theſe in Vineger, and make a Playſter and lay it to the ſore.</p>
               <p>There is no Vayne betweene the Paſtorne and the Hoofe, but the Shanke vayne: and the vayne which ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth for the Crotches, muſt be taken vp on the inſide and the outſide.</p>
               <p>Waſh it firſt with warme Vrine, then dry it with a cloth, and clip away all the haires on the Scabbie place, then rubbe and chafe it all ouer, and make faſt his feete, and rubbe the place greeued with Butter and Tarre boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling together, vpon a cloute tyed on a ſtickes ende, and bath it well therewith: vſe this once or twiſe a day till it be whole.</p>
               <p>Butter and Hony molten together is good to annoynt an Horſe for Paynes or Crotches.</p>
               <p>Take a pound of Hogges greace, i. d. worth of Verdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greace, ii. oz. of Muſtard, <hi>di.</hi> a pound of Oyle <hi>de</hi> Bay, a quarter of a pound of Naruell, <hi>di.</hi> a pound of Hony, <hi>di.</hi> a pound of Engliſh Waxe, i. oz of Arſenicke, ii. oz. of red Lead, halfe a pint of Vineger: boyle all theſe together and make an Oyntment of it: clippe the Horſe legge bare, and lay this Medecine to it very hot.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:13786:11"/>
               <head>For gourded Legges or Scratches.</head>
               <p>TAke vp the Veynes beneath the knee, and let him blood as much as you thinke good, then knit the Veyne aboue and beneath, and annoynt the Legges with this Oyle following.</p>
               <p>Take Franckenſence, and Roſen, and freſh Greace, and boyle them together, and ſtraine it, and keepe it to your vſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>A Drinke to rayſe a Horſe, or for a Horſe that is ſicke.</head>
               <p>TAke two penny worth of Pepper, two penny worſh of Saffron, two penny worth of Annis ſeedes, two penny worth of Turmeracke, a penny worth of long Pepper, two penny worth of Treacle, a penny worth of Licoris, a good quantitie of Penny-royall, and Archan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell: giue him theſe with the Polkes of Egges in Milke to drinke: And for Neate Cattle, giue theſe in drinke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a Surfet Horſe.</head>
               <p>TAke a quart of Beere or Ale, and .ii. d. worth of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let oyle, and as much Dragon water, a penny worth of Treacle: make them warme vpon the coales, and put into it a penny worth of Horſe Spices, &amp; giue it him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a Hide-bound Horſe.</head>
               <p>THis commeth by ouer working, ill dyeting, and naughty dreſſing. Take Fenne Creeke, Turme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racke, Annis ſeedes, Bayes, Lycoris, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine: beate all theſe together, and giue him one ſponefull of all theſe in Ale or Beere blood warme. This
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:13786:11"/>
is alſo good for the Cough: This will alſo keepe him from it, if you vſe to giue it him before the diſeaſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>An other for the ſame.</head>
               <p>TAke away ſome blood with a fleame, then giue him ſome warme Maſhes morning and euening and giue him Malt ſodden in water together, or Branue and Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or ſome Wheate ſodden with Barley in Water, and it will helpe him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Hoofe bound.</head>
               <p>YOu ſhall rayſe the Hoofe aboue from the toppe to the ſoole in foure or fiue places, ſo that the Water may come out: ſome do rayſe it round with a ſharpe Knife, and along downeward, and then rubbe it well with Salt once or twice.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a looſe Hoofe.</head>
               <p>TAke Tarre three ſpoonefull, of Roſen a quarter of a pound, of Tanſey, of Rue, of red Mintes, of Sothern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, of each halfe a handfull, beate them all togeather in a Morter, and put thereto halfe a pound of Butter, i. d. worth of Vergins Waxe: then fry them all together, and binde it to the Hoofe for. vii. dayes, and it will cure him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a brittle Hoofe.</head>
               <p>IF your Horſe hath a brittle Hoofe, it is becauſe he is too hot or too dry, and doth ſtand dry in the Stable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtopped.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:13786:12"/>Take Oxe doung and temper it with Vineger, and bind it warme all ouer vnto the feete, and vnder the ſooles of the feete: on the next day vſe him ſo againe, ſo vſe him for a weeke together, and it will helpe him: vſe to ſtoppe his feete with Oxe or Cow doung, or his owne, and let him ſtand ſo a moneth.</p>
               <p>Or, take the fatte of Bacon, and temper it with Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine, and annoyne his Feete therewith: which is very good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>A Medicine for the Cough, or mourning in the Chine.</head>
               <p>KEepe your Horſe meatleſſe ouer night, then take a pint and a halfe of Milke, three heades of Garlicke pilled and ſtamped, boyle them to the halfe: giue it to your Horſe, and ſome at his noſe, then runne him a quarter of a myle, then reſt him: and after that, runne him three times more, euery time reſting him then put him into the Stable and keepe him very warme, and giue him no Water till after noone, then giue him a good Meſhe: and ſo vſe him with Meſhes three dayes, and giue him no Water but alwayes warme for three dayes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>An other for the ſame.</head>
               <p>TAke Harehound, Licoris, and Anniſeedes in powder, make Balles thereof with freſh Butter, and giue it your Horſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>An other for the ſame.</head>
               <p>TAke Wheate Flower, Anniſeedes, I ſcoris, being ſtamped in a Morter, v or. vi cloues of Garlicke being bruſed: mixe all theſe together and make a Paſt of them, and roule them in Balles as bigge as a Walnut: then
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:13786:12"/>
pull out his Tongue and caſt them Balles downe his throate three or foure of them at a time, and giue two new layde Egges after them ſhels and all.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Glaunders.</head>
               <p>TAke Swines greace cleane clarifyed, and as much Oyle of Bay as a Wallnut: giue it him to drinke with faire Water luke warme.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>An other for the ſame.</head>
               <p>TAke of Elacompana, Anniſcedes, and Licoris, of each i. d. worth, boyle them in three pintes of ſtong Ale or Beere vnto two pintes or leſſe: then put into it a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a pint of Sallet Oyle, and giue it him to drinke blood warme.</p>
               <p>Then take <hi>Enforbiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> in a quill, and blow it vp into his noſe, and within three dayes after take Muſtard, Vineger, and Butter, and boyle them together: put thereto halfe an ounce of Pepper, and giue it him to drinke. Vſe the one Medecine one weeke, and the other an other, and ride or worke him eaſely.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>An other for the ſame.</head>
               <p>TAke a quantitie of Anniſeedes, Licoris, and Clacom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pana rootes, long Pepper, and Garlicke of cach a like, with three Egges and ſome Butter, a quantitie of Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſey, and ſome good Ale mixt together, and make it warme, and ſo giue it him, and keepe him warme.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:13786:13"/>
               <head>An other for the ſame.</head>
               <p>SEeth a handfull of pilled Garlicke in Milke, and put a peece of Butter thereto and ſome Ale, and ſtirre them all together and giue it him faſting, and ryde him ſoftly a while after, and then ſet him vp: but keepe him warme nine dayes after.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Strangles.</head>
               <p>CVtte him betweene the Iawes, and take out the Kirnels and waſh the place euery day wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h Beere and Butter, and ſtoppe it vp as long a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you can, and giue him new Milke and Garliake to drinke, and the iuyce of the leaues of Birch withall, or in Winter the barke of Birch: alſo ſmother him with the gumme of Maſticke or Franckenſence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Farſey.</head>
               <p>TAke blacke Sope, Arſenicke, Vnſlaked Lime, Verde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greace, and red Lead: worke theſe all together, and lay them to the ſore.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>An other for the ſame.</head>
               <p>TAke iii. oz. of Quickſiluer and put it into a Bladder, with two ſponefull of the iuyce of Orenges or Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and ſhake them together to coole the Quickſiluer: then take halfe a pound of freſh Hogges greace, and of Vergis an ounce: put all theſe in a Treene diſh, and worke them well together: then annoynt the knots with this Oyntment till they rotte, then let them out with a ſharpe knife, and annoynt them ſtill: and put into his eares the iuyce of Ragg-weede, and they will dry vp. <hi>Probatum.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:13786:13"/>
               <head>A Drinke for the Farſey.</head>
               <p>LEt him blood in the Necke on both ſides foure fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers from the Head, and giue him this drinke.</p>
               <p>Take a gallon of faire Water, and put therein a good handfull of Rue and a ſponefull of Hempſeed, and bruſe them in a Morter all together, and ſeeth it till the halfe be conſumed: and when it is cold, giue it him to drinke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Farſey.</head>
               <p>TAke blacke Sope, Muſtard made of ſharpe Wine or Vineger, and red Lead, mixe all theſe together, and annoynt the Veyne all along, rubbe it ouer with a hot Yron made of purpoſe, but very thicke: rubbe the Mede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine much in with the Yron, being red hot.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>To deſtroy the Farſey.</head>
               <p>TAke iuyce of Hemlocke a good quantitie, and bray them together, and put it into the eares, and pricke the Knottes and put in Salt, and giue him drinke with ſweete Wort, Fennell, and Treacle.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a Horſe Foote that is wrounged in the Foote-locke.</head>
               <p>SEeth a quart of Brine til the foame riſe, then ſtraine it, and put thereto a handfull of Tanſey, as much of Mallowes, a ſawcerfull of Hony, and a quarter of a pound of Sheepes Tallow: ſtirre all theſe on the fire till the Hearbes are well ſodden, and all hot, lay it to the Ioynt, and then lay a cloth ouer it, and it will be whole an three dayes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:13786:14"/>
               <head>For a wrench in the Foot-locke.</head>
               <p>TAke Pompilion, Naruile, and blacke Sope, of each a like, and heate them hot on the fire, and then annoynt him therewith.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a Horſe that is Stifled or Hipped.</head>
               <p>TAke a pound of <hi>Bole-armoniacke,</hi> one quart of red Wine-vineger, vi. Egges beaten ſhelles and all, two penny worth of Engliſh Hony, as much <hi>Venus</hi> Turpentine, one quart of Flower, one good handfull of Bay ſalt, and put all theſe in a pot, and keepe it cloſe one nyght, and the next day apply ſome of it to the hurt, dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it once a day for. ix. dayes together.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a Horſe that is Foundered.</head>
               <p>TAke Verdegreace, Turpentine, and Sallet Oyle, two or three ſponefull of Hogges greate, and Bees waxe i. oz. boyle all together, and ſo dip Flaxe or Tow in it, and ſtuffe his Feete therewith, and let him blood in the Tooes, and he ſhall be whole.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>An other for the ſame.</head>
               <p>PLucke off his Shooes and pare hollow his Feete nigh to the quicke, then race him with a crooked Launce from the Heele to the Too in two or three places on both ſides of the Hoofe and let him bleede well, then clap two or three hard Egges to it as hot as he may ſuffer it: and as they coole lay on more, and then lay hot Horſe doung vpon them and about his feete, and he will ſoone recouer, if you giue him reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:13786:14"/>
               <head>For a Horſe that is Fowndred in his Feete.</head>
               <p>TAke Tarre, Neates-foote oyle, and the Youlkes of Egges, i. d. worth of Verdegreace, and ſome wheate Branne, and boyle theſe together, and binde them vnder his foote very hot.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>If he be foundered in his Body.</head>
               <p>TAke <hi>ob.</hi> of Garlicke, ii. d. worth of the powder of Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, ii. d. worth of the powder of Ginger, ii. d. worth of Graynes bruſed, and put it into a pottle of ſtale Ale the beſt you can get, and giue it him to drinke, and lytter him to the belly, and lay cloathes on him as many as he can beare: and let him blood on the ſydes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For Blindneſſe.</head>
               <p>TAke two dry Tyſe ſtoones and rubbe them together, and blow the powder of it with a quill into his eyes three or foure times.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Webbe in the eye.</head>
               <p>TAke the leane of a Gammon of Bacon and dry it, and thereof make a powder, and vſe the powder, and it will cure it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Pearle in the Eye.</head>
               <p>TAke the iuyce of ground <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uie, the iuyce of Salandi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ae, and Womans Milke, and put it into the eyes, and it will alſo cure him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:13786:15"/>
               <head>For the Haw in the Eye.</head>
               <p>MAke a Playſter of the iuyce of Ground Iuie, and of Iuie Berries ſtamped in a Morter, beaten with Wine or Water: and Playſter wiſe lay it to the eye or eyes euening and morning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>An other for the Haw in the eye.</head>
               <p>SOme take a Needle and a double threed, and thruſt the Needle through the filme of the eye wherein the Cruſh groweth, which pull out, laying it on your fingers end, and holding the Needle and threede ſtraight, and ſo cut away all the hard matter a penny breadth. But beware you cut not away the fatt, which is the waſh of the eye: neither cut the Filme wherein the eye groweth, but cut betweene the Filme &amp; the Cruſh, &amp; then ſquirt in Beere.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a Canker in the eye.</head>
               <p>TAke Roch Allum and greene Copris of each a like, boyle them in three pintes of running Water vntill the one halfe be conſumed, then take it from the ſire, and once a day waſh his eyes therewith being made luke warme.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a ſtroke in the eye.</head>
               <p>LAy thereto the iuyce of Smalladge, Fennell, and the white of an Egge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a Windgall.</head>
               <p>TAke and cut the ſkinne, then take a ſponefull of Oyle <hi>de</hi> Bay, one ſponefull of Turpentine, i. d. worth of Verdigreace, the white of an Egge, and a quarter of an ounce of red Lead: boyle them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether and it will make a Salue, Lay the ſame to the place where you did cut him. <hi>Probatum.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <pb facs="tcp:13786:15"/>
               <head>An other for the ſame.</head>
               <p>FIrſt clippe off the haire bare, then cut it the length of a Beane and let it out, but beware of the Sinnewes that you cut not them: then haue ready molten Roſen, ſheepes Tallow, and Brimſtone boyled together: then lay on this Medecine, but beware it be not too hot.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Spauen.</head>
               <p>TAke Muſtard ſeede, &amp; Oyle <hi>de</hi> Bay, &amp; Cow doung, the rootes of Mallowes, a quantitie of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urpen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne, <hi>di.</hi> oz. of <hi>Bole-armoniacke</hi> beare them to powder and worke them together, and binde them hotte to the Spauen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the blood Spauen, and bone Spauen.</head>
               <p>TAke vp the Vaine aboue and beneath the ioynt and let it bleed well, then knit vp the Vaines, and annoynt them with Butter till they be whole.</p>
               <p>For the bone Spauen pricke it with a ſharpe poynted knife, then take a peece of Candle &amp; lay a peece of browne Paper vpon it and with a hot Yron melt the Tallow, and after noynt it with Butter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For Inflammation of the Coddes.</head>
               <p>BOyle Groundſell in Wine and Vineger, and ſo hath him therewith, and vſe to ride him into the Water.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>An other for the ſame.</head>
               <p>TAke a quart of good Alewoort and ſet it on the fyre, with the crummes of browne Bread ſtrongly leauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:13786:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and a handfull of Commine (or more) in powder: make a Playſter of all theſe and Beane flower, and apply to the griefe as hot as may be ſuffered.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>An other for the ſame.</head>
               <p>TAke new Cowdoung and ſeeth it in Milke, then make a Playſter and lay it to the griefe as hot vpon the ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling as may be.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For ſwelling of the Coddes.</head>
               <p>LEt him aſſaile a Mare, and giue him no prouender, and let him blood aboue the great vaine betweene t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ippes, and lay thereto hard Egges in his owne doung and make a Playſter of the ſame and lay it to the Coddes: and if it helpe him not, let him ſtand in the water halfe an hower.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Strangulion.</head>
               <p>TAke Bread, and Bayes of Lorell, and temper them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with May Butter, and giue him thereof three dayes together, and he ſhall be whole.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For feſtering of the Sore.</head>
               <p>TAke Lime and tough Horſe doung, and temper it to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with Pepper and the white of an Egge, and lay it to the ſore fiue dayes, and it will cure him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:13786:16"/>
               <head>A Drinke for the Stone.</head>
               <p>TAke a pint of white Wine, halfe a pint of Burre ſeed, and beat them ſmall ii. oz. of Parſeley ſeede, halfe a handfull of H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>op, halfe an oz. of blacke Sope: mingle theſe together, and warme it, and giue it him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Stone Collicke and Fret.</head>
               <p>TAke vnſet Leekes and ſtampe them ſmal, and Sope, Milke, and Butter, and giue it the Horſe, it will make him piſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a Horſe that cannot Stale.</head>
               <p>TAke a Nutmeg, and a handfull of Parſeley ſeede, beate them in powder, with a handfull of But<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, and heate it in good Ale, &amp; giue it him blood warme, and he ſhall ſtale at eaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Stone and to make him piſſe.</head>
               <p>TAke the ſeed of Smallage, Parſeley, <hi>Saxefrace.</hi> the rootes of <hi>Philu endula.</hi> Cherry-ſtones kirnelles, Gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unell ſeedes, and Broome ſeede, of euery one like much: make them in fine powder, and giue it him in white Wine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a Horſe that cannot doung.</head>
               <p>TAke. xi. leaues of Lorell and ſtampe them in a Morter, and giue it him to drinke in ſtrong ſtale Ale.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a Horſe that piſſeth blood.</head>
               <p>TAke Barley and ſeeth it in the iuyce of Gumfolly, and giue him the Barley to eate, and the iuyce to drinke.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:13786:17"/>Or elſe, take and let him Blood, and boyle the blood with the powder of the pill of Pomegranuts, and put in ſome Wheate: then ſtraine it and giue it him to drinke three or foure morninges, but let him not trauell.</p>
               <p>Take the powder of Licoris and Anniſeedes rould vp in Hony, and giue him three or foure balles of them at a time, pulling out his tongue and putting it in his throate: It looſeth his breath, and ſetteth his winde at libertie, and purgeth the cold &amp; ſtiffneſſe, and expelleth the Glaundees.</p>
               <p>Bruſed Licoris, Anniſeedes, Garlicke bruſed, a little Sallet oyle and Hony, giuen blood warme i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Milke, cureth very many diſeaſes, and keepeth him from more.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a Horſe that is broken Winded.</head>
               <p>TAke a Hedgehog and ſplit him, and take out his guttes and dry them vp in an Ouen vntill you make powder of them, giue it your Horſe to drinke in a pint of good Ale, a part thereof, then make Bals of Annyſeedes and Licorie rowled in Butter, and caſt them downe his throat: and waſh his Oates in good Ale or Beere, then take Commin, Annyſeedes. Licoris, and Sentatie, and make powder of them, and ſtrew threee ſponefull in his Oates, being moyſt: vſe this ſome .xiiii. dayes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>An other if he be Purſey.</head>
               <p>TAke Moll ne or Longwort and make a powder there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and giue it him to drinke with Water, and it will heale him.</p>
               <p>Or, you may take the powder of <hi>Genſian</hi> at the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries, and that will heale him alſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:13786:17"/>
               <head>For a Horſe pricked with a Nayle.</head>
               <p>TAke out the Hoofe till you come to the bottome or Vayne, then take Turpentine i. oz. Tarre i. oz. Pitch i. oz. Beefe ſuet i. oz. and one head of Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke: boyle them all together, and lay them to it ſo hot as may be ſuffred: And if it chaunce to breake out aboue the Hoofe, then take the ſayd Medecine and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynt it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>To heale a Mangie Horſe.</head>
               <p>LEt him blood on both ſides of his Necke, then cut the Skinne in the middeſt of his Fore-head two fingers broad, then rayſe the ſkinne on both ſides, and put in ſlyces of Angellica roote, or Elacompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na: leaue them till it rotte, thruſt out the matter, but leaue the rootes, they will come out as it healeth, annoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the mangie places with the powder of Brimſtone and Verdigreace mixed with Oyle Ollife.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>An other for the ſame.</head>
               <p>TAke Lampe Oyle, fine powder of Brimſtone, of blacke Sope, Tarre, Barrow-hogges greace, &amp; the Sutte of a Chimnie, of each a like, &amp; then mixe them all together, and annoynt the place therewith ſo hotte as may be ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and it will helpe him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Mangie of a Dogge.</head>
               <p>TAke Vineger, Gon-powder, blacke Sope, Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, burnt Allum, and Verdigreace: boyle all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with Hony, and rub ouer the mangie place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:13786:18"/>
               <head>For the String-hale.</head>
               <p>TAke vp the M. Vaine aboue the Knee, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neath the ſame Vaine lyeth a String, cut it away: then cut him below in the Noſtrilles, and take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way two ſtringes, and then annoynt him with But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Salt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Mares Euill.</head>
               <p>TAke Milke, Otemeale, Mallowes, Woormewood, Horehound, and Sn. allage, wring theſe together with your handes, and boyle them together till they be ſoft, and lay it to the griefe, which will bring it to a head: then you muſt launce it: then take red Lead, burnt Allum, and Roſen, beat theſe to powder, and caſt vpon it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>To take away Bones, Knobbes, or Ring-bones.</head>
               <p>TAke a pound of Strong Lie and Sope, a quarter of <hi>Vitreall Romane,</hi> i. oz. of <hi>Salarmonick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> aſmuch of Roch Allum, and boyle them together till they are thicke, and ſo vſe it for an Oyntment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gipſiacum</hi> the ſtrongeſt kind, lay it on with Cotten three or foure times, will take it away. This is good alſo for a Splint: and though it he a Thiſtula in the Crowne it will ſinke it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Powle Fuill: which commeth of a bruſe behind the Eares.</head>
               <p>TAke a hat Yron, but firſt take vp the haire all the whole compaſſe, then feare it with the Yron, and then take red Lead and blacke Sope, and mingle them
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:13786:18"/>
with Water and make it thicke, and annoynt him withall, till it be whole.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>To make a Water for the ſame.</head>
               <p>TAke a quart of Water, halfe a pound of Roch Allum, iiii. d. worth of Mercurie, a quarter of a pound of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digreace: and when you ſee the Horſe rubbe his head, waſh him with this water.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>An other for the ſame.</head>
               <p>LAy a Playſter of Hogges greace on to ripe the place, and when it is ripe, launce it, and thruſt thorow a hot Iron, if it be very deepe, and keepe it open with Tentes made of a Spunge, and dippe it in Hogges greace: vſe this for foure dayes, then take Turpentine, and the yolkes of Egges, and Saffron, and mingle them well together, and dippe your Tentes of Spung therein, and be ſure they goe to the bottome, and playſter it with Hogges greace: and this will cure him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Camer.</head>
               <p>YOu muſt take out his Tongue and let him blood in fiue or ſixe places, and likewiſe on his vpper Lippe, that he may bleed well, and all berubbe his Tongue and Lippes with Salt: then the next day waſh his Tongue and Lippes with Vineger, and rubbe it againe with Salt, and giue him warme drinke and new Beere a day or two.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Coult Euill.</head>
               <p>TAke the iuyce of Hemlocke and waſhe his Pear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Coddes therewith.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:13786:19"/>
               <head>An other for the ſame.</head>
               <p>TAke Beaneflower, Vineger, and Bolarmoniacke, and worke theſe together, and lay it to the Coddes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>An other for the ſame.</head>
               <p>YOu may waſh his Shed with warme Vineger, and draw foorth his Yarde and waſh it alſo: then ride him into the water, let him ſwimme, and there toſſe and turne him: vſe this two or three weekes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Cloying.</head>
               <p>IF he halt, pull off his Shoo and open the place pricked with a knife, and powre in Turpentine, Waxe, and Sheepes ſuet being molten together: then cloſe it vp and ſet on the Shoo againe: let him reſt, and come in n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wet ground.</p>
               <p>Some do vſe to burne the hole with a hot Yron when they haue pult out the Nayle, and ſome do powre in boyled Butter in the hole once a day, and it hath cured it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>An other for the ſame.</head>
               <p>TAke a handfull of Nettles, of blacke Sope, of Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, of each a ſpoonefull, &amp; three times ſo much Boares greace or Bacon greace, then ſtampe them well together, and ſtoppe the ſore therewith and it will not rot any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but heale, although you labor him.</p>
               <p>Some do ſtoppe vp the hole when they draw foorth the Nayle, with Tallow and Horſe doung, and then ſet on the Shoo.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:13786:19"/>
               <head>For the Cordes.</head>
               <p>THe cure is to ſlit it, and with a Buckes horne to take it vp, and tie it in two places, and cut it away.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>An other for the ſame.</head>
               <p>TAke Muſtard, and Aqua-vice, and Sallet Oyle, and voyle them on the Coales, and make a Playſter and binde it hot to the Place. It is good alſo for any Straine, ſo it be new done.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>An other for the ſame.</head>
               <p>TAke the groundes of Ale, and being made warme, bath his Legs therewith, and wiſpe him with a Maye rope.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>An other for a Spraine.</head>
               <p>TAke ſmallage, and an Hearbe called Oxeye, and ſome Sheepes ſuet: choppe them all together and boyle it in mens Vrine, and bath the place therewith, and wet a Hay band in it, and rowle vp the Leg therewith. <hi>Prob.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Curbes.</head>
               <p>FRet his Legges with thy hand, and then take red Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort leaues, and Burrage, and bray them together, and lay it thereto v. dayes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Againſt ſtifneſſe of Sinniewes.</head>
               <p>SEeth a pound of blacke Sope in a quart of ſtrong Ale till it looke like Tarre, and annoynt the Sinniewes therewith, and it will ſupple them, and bring them to the right courſe. It is good for a Man if he be ſtiffe in the Ioyntes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For Enterfeering.</head>
               <p>HEe may be much holpen by ſhooing with a ſkilfull Smith: But if the ſkinne be off, Take May Butter,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:13786:20"/>
with a quantitie of yellow Roſen, as much Maruell, then fry them together in a Panne, and let it ſtand till it be cold, and put it in a Potte, and put to it a little new Cow doung, and make Playſters thereof &amp; binde it to the place. This will heale alſo the pricke of a Nayle.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Nauell galled.</head>
               <p>TAke Sutte of a Chimney and Yeeſt, mixed together, and playſter it on; but ſhift it once a day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>An other for the ſame.</head>
               <p>TAke Nettle ſeedes, and mixe them with Sallet Oyle, and annoynt the Sort or Chaſing therewith.</p>
               <p>Some do vſe to waſh him with warme Water and then annoynt the place with Greace and Salt mixed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>An other for the ſame</head>
               <p>TAke hearbe Bittonie, Brimſtone in powder, of <hi>Ebbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> Pitch, and olde Greace, and ſtampe them together: and when you haue waſhed him with Chamber Lie, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynt him with this Medicine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>A Water for a Gawled Backe, or any foule Sore.</head>
               <p>TAke a pottle of Varnice, iii. d. worth of greene Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pris, and boyle it to the one halfe or more, and waſh the Sore with that, and then fill the Sore with redde Lead, and let it not be dreſſed of three dayes, and then dreſſe him againe as you ſhall ſee cauſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:13786:20"/>
               <head>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cene Wound.</head>
               <p>TAke white Wine and make it warme, and waſh the Wound therewith, then take Turpentine, <hi>Mell Roſap</hi> and a little Waxe, and melt them together, being ſtirred continually till they are well mixed, and then vſe it. If it be a Cutte, take Cow and dippe it therein, and fill the wound with it: If it be a hole, make Tentes for the place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>An other for the ſame.</head>
               <p>TAke Hogges Greace, and <hi>Venus</hi> Turpentine, and melt them together: and if it be a Cutte, take Cow and dippe therein, and fill the wound therewith: If it be a hole, make Tentes, and dreſſe it therewith.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a hot Impoſtume in any outward part.</head>
               <p>STmpe Liuerwort, and mixe it with the groundes of Ale, Mallowes, and Hogges greace, being made hot, and layde thereto.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>An other for the ſame.</head>
               <p>BRuſe Lettis ſeedes, and Poppie ſeedes, and mixe them with Oyle of red Roſes, and playſter wiſe lay it to the ſore.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a cold Impoſtume.</head>
               <p>TAke the hearbe Balme ſtamp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd mixed with Hogs greace, and playſter wiſe lay it t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:13786:21"/>
               <head>An other for the ſame.</head>
               <p>SEeth white Mintes in Wine or Ale, with Oyle or But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and lay it hot to the place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>To ripe any Impoſtume.</head>
               <p>SEeth Mallows rootes and Lillie rootes, and then bruſe them, and put thereto Hogges greace, and Linſeede Meale: and playſterwiſe lay it to it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Rume.</head>
               <p>LEt him blood in the Vaine vnder the Tayle, and rub his Gummes with Sage tyed to a Stickes ende, and giue him for a while the tender croppes of Blacke Bryers in his Prouender.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For looſe Teeth.</head>
               <p>PRicke the Gummes with a knife, and then rybbe them with Hony, Sage, and Salt, beaten together. The Sorrell Horſe is moſt ſubiect to this diſeaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Feuer.</head>
               <p>LEt him blood in the Thigh in the middle Vayne ſhire fingers vnder his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uell: or elſe take the Vayne in the Nerke, and giue him a drinke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>An othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</head>
               <p>TAke Water &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Gumme, Dragane<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> in powder, with a few of Dammaſke R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> them all together, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> him to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
